A Guide to the Orange County (Va.) Marriage Bonds, Ministers' Returns and Index, Volumes 1-16, 1775-1854
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Orange County (Va.) Marriage Bonds, Ministers' Returns and Index, Volumes 1-16, 1775-1854
Library of Virginia
1146784-1146788, 1124301, 1124304-1124306, 1124334-1124341, 1129137
18 vol. (4139 p.) Barcodes 1146785-1146788, 1124301, 1124304-1124306 and 1124334-1124341 are negative photostatic copies. Barcode 1146784 is a typescript photocopy. Barcode 1129137 is an original compilation.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Use microfilm copies, Orange County, Reels 48-56.
Acquisition Information
The original volume was compiled and created by The Daughters of the American Revolution (DAR) from the original court records found in the Orange County Circuit Court Clerk's Office. The original index was compiled by the Virginia State Library's (now the Library of Virginia) Archives Division from the DAR-created volumes--now found in the Orange County Circuit Court Clerk's Office.
The negative photostatic copies of the volumes were created by the Virginia State Library's (now the Library of Virginia) Archives Division from the original DAR-created volumes. The typescript photocopy of the index was created by the Virginia State Library's (now the Library of Virginia) Archives Division from the original compilation. The microfilm copies of these volumes were generated by The Library of Virginia's Imaging Services Branch.
Historical Information
Orange County was formed in 1734 from Spotsylvania County. According to most accounts, the county was named for William of Orange, the Dutch prince who became William III of England in 1688. It is more probable, however, that the name honored William IV, prince of Orange-Nassau, who married Anne, eldest daughter of George II, in 1734.
Prior to 1853, when the Commonwealth began recording vital statistics, Virginia marriages were recorded at the county or city level. Beginning in 1661, in order to be married by license, the groom was required to go before the county clerk and give bond with security that there was no lawful reason to prevent the marriage. The license, issued then by the clerk, was given to the minister who performed the service. Written consent from a parent or guardian was needed for individuals younger than twenty-one years.
Scope and Content
Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volumes 1-16, 1775-1854, record the original bonds of marriage between a bride and groom within the county. This volume also contains original marriage consents and ministers' returns--made by individual ministers of marriages performed within the county. These returns took the form of lists which record the date of marriage and names of both parties. In Volume 16,1848-1854, marriage certificates and licenses are included.
An Index to Marriage Bonds, 1775-1854, is a separate volume--covering Orange County Marriage Bond Books 1-16. It is arranged alphabetically from A-Y by the last and first names of both parties. At the top of each page, the parties are listed in one or all of the three main categories (marriage consents, marriage bonds and ministers' returns.) The volume and page number follow these references. As the index indicates, "li" means no marriage bond but indicates that a marriage license has been recorded. The index also contains alternate spellings and/or variations of last names. Unlike the volumes, this index is not available on microfilm.
Arrangement
Chronological.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Orange County Marriage Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. See A Guide to County and City Records on microfilm at www.lva.lib.va.us/whatwehave/local/local_rec/index.htm.
Separated Material
Volumes 5-16 and the original compiled index to the volumes are found at the Library of Virginia's State Records Center.
Access Terms
Orange County (Va.). Circuit Court.; Clergy--Virginia--Orange County.; Marriage--Virginia--Orange County.; Orange County (Va.)--History.; Indexes (reference sources)--Virginia--Orange County.; Local government records--Virginia--Orange County.; Marriage bonds--Virginia--Orange County.; Marriage consents--Virginia--Orange County.; Marriage licenses--Virginia--Orange County.; Marriage records--Virginia--Orange County.; Ministers' returns--Virginia--Orange County.
Contents List
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 1, 1775-1788, 1146785
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 2, 1787-1793, 1146786
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 3, 1792-1796, 1146787
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 4, 1796-1800, 1146788
- Index to Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volumes 1-16, 1775-1854, 1146784
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 5, 1800-1803, 1124304
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 6, 1804-1809, 1124305
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 7, 1809-1813, 1124306
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 8, 1813-1817, 1124334
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 9, 1817-1821, 1124335
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 10, 1821-1825, 1124336
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 11, 1825-1829, 1124337
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 12, 1829-1833, 1124338
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 13, 1833-1836, 1124339
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 14, 1837-1842, 1124301
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 15, 1843-1848, 1124340
- Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volume 16, 1848-1854, 1124341
- Index to Marriage Bonds and Ministers' Returns, Volumes 1-16 (Original Compilation), 1775-1854, 1129317